Guide to New Neighbors: Sunset Park's Chinese Community oral histories 1994.007
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Leung, Yee Ming, 1993 September 8; 1994.007.19
  Yee Ming Leung was born in Hong Kong, China circa 1958, immigrated to America at age eleven, and settled in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. Leung attended public schools during school integration; the experience shaped his views of the American melting pot. After attending the University of the Pacific, Leung spent ten years in California as a teacher and owner of an import-export business. He returned to New York City to help his sister's growing restaurant business. Leung became a restaurateur himself with the opening of Oriental Palace in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the interview in 1993, Leung sat on Community Board 4 and had recently lost his first campaign for a seat on the school board of District 20.
  In this interview, Yee Ming Leung describes his teenage assimilation to American culture; a childhood of "Chinese" activities such as catching crabs on Coney Island or stealing nuts from neighbors' trees, as well as playing baseball and watching football or movies with his new American friends. Leung recalls his life as a businessman and, later, a restaurateur. He discusses his campaign and motivations for running for a seat on the School Board, Chinese attitudes towards voting, and his activities as an activist and member of Community Board 4. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Community Board No. 4 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Leung, Yee Ming; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); California; Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Cultural assimilation; Elections |x Corrupt practices |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Hong Kong (China); Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School districts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Li, Miu Fei, 1993 December 19; 1994.007.20
  Miu Fei Li was born in Mainland China in 1959. In 1981 she followed her husband to New York City and settled in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan. She became a professional seamstress, joined the local seamstress' union, and had two children. After finding work out-of-state, Li's husband became addicted to gambling; after racking up tens of thousands of dollars of debt, they divorced. In 1993, Li married a fellow divorcee whom she met while on vacation in Hong Kong. At the time of the interview that same year, Miu Fei Li was living with her new husband and their combined four children in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Miu Fei Li discusses life since her 1981 immigration to New York City. She tells of the decision to immigrate to America as a twenty-two year-old newlywed; initial impressions of Manhattan; and attempts to learn English. She describes life and working conditions experienced as a garment factory seamstress and the benefits of being a union member. She talks about her work schedule; which played roles in fostering her husband's gambling addiction and their subsequent divorce. Li speaks of her second marriage. She also evaluates real estate conditions in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn circa 1993. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; Li, Miu Fei; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Divorce; Factories |z New York (State) |z New York; Guangdong Sheng (China); Home economics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Working class |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Li, Ning-Yuan and Anonymous, 1993 July 2; 1994.007.21
  Ning-Yuan Li was born in 1936 in Nanjing, China to an educated family, and as a teenager became an award-winning fine arts painter. At the time of the interview, he had been in America for four years and had a school-aged daughter. J.L. (Anonymous) was born in Burma, but soon moved to Taiwan. During the "Anti-Japan War," J.L. was orphaned and subsequently joined the fight against the Japanese invasion. Later, he moved to Paraguay and Brazil, where he started a small wrist-watch business. He immigrated to America in 1984. At the time of the interview, he had a daughter in kindergarten. J.T. (Anonymous) also provides narration. Her own full-length oral history (1994.007.03) is available as part of this collection.
  In this interview, J.L. (Anonymous) and Ning-Yuan Li provide viewpoints on their different lives that led them to America. Li, fine art painter, describes his early education and sensibilities as an artist and recalls the Chinese Cultural Revolution's impact on fine art in China. J.L., from Taiwan, relates his life story; the era of the "Anti-Japan War," his career as a soldier, and time spent in Paraguay running a small wrist-watch business. Joined by J.T. (Anonymous, also a narrator of her own oral history), J.L. and Li discuss their shared experience as residents of Brooklyn's Chinatown; working conditions for Chinese immigrants, language barriers, armed robberies, and the American systems of education and juvenile corrections. Interview in Mandarin conducted by Gregory Ruf.
  Li, Ning-Yuan; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976; Anti-Japanese War, 1937-1945; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Burma; Central America; China; China |x History |x Cultural Revolution, 1966-1976; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Communism |z China; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education; Immigrants; Law enforcement |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political corruption |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public welfare |z New York (State) |z Kings County; South America; Taiwan (China); Taiwanese Americans; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Work environment |z United States
- Mak, Paul, 1993 March 26; 1994.007.22
  Paul Mak was born in Hong Kong, China, and immigrated to New York City at around age sixteen. Priced out of the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan, his family settled into Brooklyn. After completing high school in Brooklyn, Mak graduated from Hunter College with a degree in computer hardware programming. Unable to quickly find a job in programming, Mak entered into a career of civil service. In 1988 Mak helped found the Brooklyn Chinese American Association, an influential Eighth Avenue-based business services organization. At the time of the 1993 interview, Mak was the only Asian community board member in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In this interview, Paul Mak discusses his personal assimilation into mainstream American culture. He details his career as a civil servant serving the Chinese community of Eighth Avenue in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Sunset Park; helping educate new immigrants assimilate by teaching them American customs, smoothing out relationships with neighboring ethnic groups (particularly the Latino community), and working to develop Brooklyn's Chinatown by facilitating the migration of garment factories from Manhattan to Brooklyn. He also describes his time as a community board member. Interview conducted by Mary Lui.
  Brooklyn Chinese American Association.; Mak, Paul; Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Civil service |z New York (State); Community organizing |z New York (State) |z New York; Cultural assimilation; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Hong Kong (China); Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Ngu, Thien Thuy, 1993 September 7; 1994.007.23
  Ngu, Thien Thuy; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Quinones, Edmundo, 1994 June 10; 1994.007.24
  Edmundo Quinones was born circa 1946 in Manhattan to Puerto Rican immigrant parents, and grew up in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. As Latinos, the Quinones were discriminated against -- still, he remembers a childhood of mixed play in his working-class neighborhood with stick-ball and water balloons. At age fourteen Quinones moved to Puerto Rico. When he re-settled in New York City he found the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn to be inhabited primarily by Latinos. He married a Puerto Rican woman and had two sons. Around 1985, Quinones stumbled upon Brooklyn's Chinatown and was amazed to find the Chinese American community so quickly well-established.
  In this interview, Edmundo Quinones discusses his life as a first-generation working-class Puerto Rican American. He reflects on the challenges he's faced as a Latino growing up in a White neighborhood; particularly discrimination, and strengthening his Latino identity while avoiding mainstream assimilation. He provides an overarching view on the American dream: class mobility (both upward and downward), ethnic relations, and neighborhood change. He describes the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bay Ridge's transformation from a predominantly poor Scandinavian enclave, to a Latino area called Sunset Park, to a bustling, predominantly Chinese American community. Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf and Fabiana Chiu.
  Quinones, Edmundo; American Dream; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Rico; San Juan (P.R); Scandinavian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Social classes; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Ung, Po Yee, 1993 August 17; 1994.007.25
  Po Yee Ung, born in Hong Kong circa 1957, immigrated to New York City at age twenty-five to accept a job offer. She settled in the Brighton Beach neighborhood of Brooklyn. As a young career woman in Tai Po, China, Ung worked in both the garment and electronics industries. In New York City, she worked primarily as a journalist; writing for Chinese-language print newspapers and weeklies, reporting and interviewing for Chinese-language Apple Television, and writing a column for a Chinese-language entertainment weekly. At the time of the 1993 interview, Ung was thirty-six years old, lived alone in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, and earned a living as an insurance saleswoman.
  In this interview, Po Yee Ung discusses her external world. She recounts her professional life: a Hong Kong career in business, and a New York City career in journalism. Ung evaluates Eighth Avenue's potential as a business and cultural center for Chinese immigrants in Brooklyn, and its deficiencies as a community resource. Ung recounts instances of petty neighborhood crime. She describes the neighborhood's aesthetic and real estate conditions. She talks about her affinity for Spanish-speaking sections of the neighborhood; particularly Hispanic food, customs, and people. Throughout the interview, Ung declines to answer questions that she views as too personal, or which may indicate her general whereabouts. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Ka-Kam Chui.
  Leung, Yee Ming; Ung, Po Yee; Brighton Beach (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Home economics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hong Kong (China); Journalists |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Wong, Chun Wai, 1993 May 26 and 28; 1994.007.26
  Chun Wai "Billy" Wong was born in Hong Kong, China in 1964. He came to the United States with his family in 1984 and they settled in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. His grandparents had come to America years earlier and they helped the family immigrate. Wong's mother worked in factories in the Chinatown neighborhood of Manhattan and his father worked in a restaurant in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. Wong worked as a youth Counselor and trip coordinator for youth in an afterschool program at a public middle school. He also studied computer science at Brooklyn College and then transferred to City College. He worked as a computer programmer for one year after he graduated. While working part-time as a youth counselor and studying at Hunter College, Wong began to teach dancing in the after school program at P.S. 220.
  In this interview, Chun Wai "Billy" Wong discusses his arrival to America and living in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn as compared to his birthplace of Hong Kong, China. He cites reasons why he likes living in New York. Wong describes the culture and lifestyle of the working Chinese community; the differences between Mainland Chinese people and Chinese people from Hong Kong, the means in which the Chinese travel back and forth from the neighborhoods, shopping at food stores, and banking. Wong evaluates the economic changes in the two communities; new garment factories in Brooklyn, unionization, and health insurance in the factories in New York. Wong speaks about his job as a public school youth counselor; the characteristics of different groups of Chinese youth and problems with gang activity. He recalls his education as a computer programmer in the City University of New York’s colleges and work after graduation. He recounts his shift to study dance at Hunter College while working as a youth counselor. Wong talks about Chinese-American family life; including home ownership and celebrating various American holidays within their community. He also sees changes in Sunset Park as it becomes more populated. Interview conducted by Mary Lui.
  Wong, Chun Wai; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese American families |z New York (State) |z New York; Chinese Americans |x Employment; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Illegal aliens |z United States; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Wong, Fook, Reverend, 1993 April 15; 1994.007.27
  Called by a relative to bring the word of Jesus Christ to Brooklyn's Chinese community, Reverend Fook "Samuel" Wong, at age forty-two, immigrated with his wife to New York City from Hong Kong in 1982. In 1983, they established the Chinese Promise Baptist Church in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. Through the church, Wong and his wife founded an annual Memorial Day Weekend street festival, which they hoped would increase neighborhood vitality and pride, while reducing street crime. At the time of the 1993 interview, Wong's daily activities were spent in community service; preaching, providing charity, organizing the annual street festival, and tending to the needs of his fifty parishioners.
  In this interview Reverend Fook "Samuel" Wong discusses his life as an evangelical Baptist preacher in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. He talks about the innermost lives of the immigrant Chinese community he works with daily, detailing their "stages of immigration," as they assimilate to American culture. He details the domestic and financial challenges faced by overworked immigrants. Wong speaks on other issues, including corrupted youth, Chinese gang-related activities, the diversity of Brooklyn's Chinatown, and ethnic tensions between the area's Hispanic and Chinese residents. He also describes the Fuzhou people of China. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Mary Lui.
  Chinese Promise Baptist Church (New York, N.Y.).; Wong, Fook, Reverend; American Dream; Baptist associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baptists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); China; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Evangelistic work |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Wong, Guillermo and Wong, Norma, 1994 June 10; 1994.007.28
  Married couple Guillermo and Norma Wong immigrated to Brooklyn, New York from Lima, Peru in 1980 to escape political, social, and economic unrest there. Because Guillermo Wong (who was half-Chinese) and Norma Wong both greatly appreciated Chinese culture, the Wong family felt at ease on their mixed Latino-Chinese street in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the 1994 interview, the Wongs had been married twenty-four years, had three sons, and felt assimilated into American culture. They had recently begun a network marketing business which they hoped would offer financial freedom and the opportunity to buy a home.
  In this interview, Guillermo and Norma Wong discuss their unique situation as a Chinese-Peruvian family living in a Chinese-Latino section of the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn; facing anti-Chinese slurs made by Latino residents, for example. They describe the ethnic makeup of their neighborhood, the politics of ethnic identity, racism, and discrimination. The Wongs recall the challenges of making it in America; finding housing, learning English, finding a job, and understanding American culture. Interview conducted by Gregory Ruf and Fabiana Chiu.
  Wong, Guillermo; Wong, Norma; Astoria (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; English as a second language; Ethnic identity; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Hispanic Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants; Multiculturalism; Peru; Peruvian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Queens County (N.Y.); Racism |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Zhu, Yu Rong, 1993 April 23; 1994.007.29
  Yu Rong Zhu, born in 1927 in Taishan, China, lived through the Japanese Invasion of China, the Chinese Civil War, and the Cultural Revolution. Zhu's status as a civil engineer protected him from governmental persecution, and he was satisfied with life. But his children, who lost educational and professional opportunities to the Cultural Revolution, urged him to immigrate to America. With his wife, Zhu moved to San Francisco in 1988; his children soon followed. At the time of the interview, Zhu was sixty-six years old and lived in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn with his wife and eldest daughter.
  In this interview, Yu Rong Zhu discusses his first sixty years of life, in which he witnessed the Japanese Invasion, the Chinese Civil War, and the Cultural Revolution. He reflects on the decision to move to America, his first two years in San Francisco, and his subsequent move to Brooklyn's Chinatown (or the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn). Zhu compares the lifestyle, living conditions, and apartment rental situation in the Chinatown communities of Brooklyn and Manhattan. He considers neighborhood crime, inter-ethnic relations, and the difficulties of life as a Chinese immigrant. Interview in Cantonese conducted by Mary Lui.
  Zhu, Yu Rong; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); China; China |x History |y 20th century; Chinatown (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Chinatown (New York, N.Y.); Chinese Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Communism |z China; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic relations; Guangzhou (China); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; San Francisco (Calif.); Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 2: Oral history transcripts, 1993-1996
- Series 3: Administrative materials, 1992-1996